Guide to the Gail Donohue Storey Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Gail Donohue Storey Papers
1974-2016
03/2001-002
Storey, Gail Donohue
9.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Other Information: Uploaded to TARO 6/14/07 Additional information may be found at https://txarchives.org/uhsc/finding_aids/00043.xml
This series includes articles, an artists' book, essays, a libretto, poetry, notes, notebooks and her UH thesis Psychic Kissing, which evolved into the novel The Lord's Motel. Items, both published and unpublished, are in alphabetical order by format and then by title.
Biographical Information:
Gail Donohue Storey was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts on July 15, 1947. She earned a B.A. from Rosary College in 1969, a M.S. in Library Science from the University of Illinois in 1973, a M.A. in liberal education from John's College in 1982, and a M.A. in English and Creative Writing from the University of Houston also in 1982. Storey is the author of I Promise Not to Suffer: A Fool for Love Hikes the Pacific Crest Trail, The Lord's Motel, God's Country Club, First Poems of Gail Donohue, articles, essays, and works of short fiction.
Storey has won numerous honors and awards, including, for I Promise Not to Suffer, the National Outdoor Book Award (2013), Foreword/IndieFab Book of the Year (2013), Nautilus Silver Award (2014), Colorado Book Award (2014), Barbara Savage Award (2013), Boulder Writers' Workshop Best Memoir (2013), and finalist, Colorado Authors' League Award (2014) and Next Generation Indie Book Award (2014). God's Country Club was a Barnes & Noble Discover Great New Writers Selection (1996). She also won New Millennium Writings Honorable Mentions in Nonfiction in 2010 and 2009, the My Table Magazine Haiku Competition in 1999, the Best Fiction Award from the South Central Women's Studies Association in 1998, finalist in fiction for the Austin Writers' League Violet Crown Book Award in 1997, finalist in fiction for the PEN Texas Writing Awards in 1997, the PEN Southwest Discovery Prize, second honorable mention in 1989, finalist in 1988 and 1984, and first runner up for fiction in 1983, an honorable mention from the Cultural Arts Council of Houston in 1987, Texas Fiction Contest runner-up in 1985, first prize for fiction for the Houston Orange Show in 1985; a Yaddo fellowship in 1987 and Virginia Center for the Creative Arts fellowship in 1985, the Houston Festival Prose Award in 1983, New Poetic Drama first honorable mention in 1981, and the Elliott Coleman Award, second honorable mention in 1980.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston -- Alumni and alumnae; University of Houston. Creative Writing Program
Genre/Form of Material:
Essays; Personal papers; Poems
Personal Name:
Storey, Gail Donohue
Topical Term:
Authors -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century
Acquisition Information:
This collection was donated to the University of Houston Libraries by Gail Donohue Storey in 2002. Additional materials arrived 2012-2015.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection is divided into five series: Short Writings, Short Fiction, Novels, Promotional Materials, and Personal Materials. The first three series are arranged in alphabetical order by title and the last two series are arranged in chronological order.
Detailed List of Contents
- Short Writings, 1974-2000
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes articles, an artists' book, essays, a libretto, poetry, notes, notebooks and her UH thesis Psychic Kissing, which evolved into the novel The Lord's Motel. Items, both published and unpublished, are in alphabetical order by format and then by title.
  - Articles
    - A Maine Escape, November 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Homeless in Houston, November 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Homeless in Houston, Transcribed Tapes (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - Houston-A "Wild West" Metropolis, February 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Houston Man, December 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Things we do for Love, February 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Writing Our Own Story as Doctors and Nurses, Spring 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Artists' Book
    - Amber Goes to Yoga (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Essays
    - Cockroach Consciousness, April 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Freeway Fantasia, The Talk of the Freeways, June 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lyric Voice in "640" by Emily Dickinson, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Libretto
    - The Psychiatrist & From One Room to Another [unpublished], 1983-84 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes correspondence and interview of Gail Donohue Storey in Opera American Style, Strides, Vol. 1, 1983.
  - Poetry
    - Beachmont, May 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - First Poems of Gail Donohue, Pine Street Press, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Copyedited typescript of First Poems (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Page Proof of First Poems (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Paper samples, style pages, and order form for First Poems (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Haiku-Sine 217 Tiny Food Poems by Texans..., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ocean & Dreams Rising, April 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Timepiece, Matrix II, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Poetic Drama: The Longing & Claire, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Thesis, University of Houston
    - Psychic Kissing [computer discs], December 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Psychic Kissing [bound copy], December 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Editor's and Publisher’s Correspondence re: “Psychic Kissing,” “You” and others, 1983-1989 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Workshop pieces
    - Articles, "Bag Lady" (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Dreams" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "I" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Diagnosis" (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Plot; theme; titles; chapter headings (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Fiction in progress, fragments, leftovers (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Party fragments" (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Tribute to Cosmic Absurdity" (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Texas" (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Ideas" (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Father" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Other episodes" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "The Poison Ivy League and other humorous writings" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Ireland" (Box 2, Folder 14)
      1985 trip - brochures, maps, tourist information
  - Notebooks and Note Cards, 1980s
  - Graduate School Writing
    - Writings from time as a UH Graduate Student (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Short Fiction, 1982-2010
  This series contains short stories as well as rejection letters from various publishers. The arrangement is alphabetical by title.
  - Anesthesia, 1984-85 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Baby Hood and Freedom, October 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cookies in Bed, November 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Francis [unpublished], 1984-85 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Freeways and Freedom, October 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Geometry Hotline, 1984-85 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Honeymoon Cottage, 1982-83 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - I Exist By Myself in My Love for It, 1983-85 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - I Know How to Make You Happy If I Feel Like It, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - The Little City [unpublished], 1982-92 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Psychic Kissing, 1982-86 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Reading Other People's Mail, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - The Room Where I Lay Dreaming, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Shortie Stories for Busy People, 1984-86 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Sperm No. 186, from The Bad Girls Dinner Party, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Today's A Sure Thing, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Totally Nude Live Girls, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Violence: A Meditation, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Wind, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 18a)
  - Your Mother and I [unpublished], 1984-86 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Novels and Memoirs, 1989-2016
  This series contains typescripts, computer discs, and proofs of The Lord's Motel, God's Country Club, and I Promise Not to Suffer (originally titled "I Never Cared Much for Nature).
  - The Lord's Motel
    - You - first typescript of The Lord's Motel, May 1989 (Box 7, Folder 20-22)
    - Psychic Kissing - third typescript draft of The Lord's Motel, August 1990 (Box 7, Folder 23-25)
    - Later typescript draft, May 1991 (Box 7, Folder 26-28)
    - Typescript draft with corrections, letter from Karen Braziller, and notes from Tracy Daugherty (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - Various typescripts with corrections, June 1991 (Box 8, Folder 4-8)
    - Copyedited typescript, September 1991 (Box 8, Folder 9-11)
    - Page proofs with corrections, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Uncorrected bound galley proof, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - God's Country Club
    - Computer discs (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Uncorrected bound galley proof, May 1996 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Book Tours for The Lords Motel and God’s Country Club, 1992-1996 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - I Promise Not to Suffer
    - Correspondence, Biographical, Story (Porter Storey), Poem (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Full Draft - I Never Cared Much for Nature - later titled I Promise Not to Suffer, September 19, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Chapters of I Never Much Cared for Nature - with Writing Group Notes (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
    - Blog posts (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Blog Posts - GailStorey.com (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Guest Blog Posts (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Awards (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Events and Publicity Phots (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Book Tour (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Excerpts (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Interviews (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Mountaineer Books Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Promotion/Publicity Materials (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Website Printouts (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Promotional Materials, 1992-2009
  This series contains reviews, excerpts, articles, quotes, photographs, and biographical information arranged in chronological order.
  - The Lord's Motel
    - Review - New York Times Book Review, August 30, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Excerpt - Villages Magazine, September 1992 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Article and Cover Photo - Library Journal, October 1, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Reviews - various publications, 1992-3 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Articles - various newspapers, 1992-5 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Article - The Writer's Chronicle, March/April, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Excerpt - The World and I, January 1993 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Quote - Entertainment Weekly, February 11, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Quote - Signature Works, April-July 1994 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - God's Country Club
    - Photographs and post cards, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Review - Barnes & Noble Discover Great New Writers, Fall 1996 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Review - Houston Chronicle, September 22, 29, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 27)
      includes pamphlet of 17th Annual Book & Author Dinner
    - Excerpt - My Table, October/November 1996 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Reviews - various publications, 1996-7 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Excerpt - WIVLA-Women in the Visual and Literary Arts, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Article - San Antonio Express-News, S.A. Life section, March 9, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Biographical information, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - (Ovs folder 1)
      - Poster for St. John's School Book Fair with news article, "A Life Storey" by Fritz Lanham (Ovs folder 1, Item 1)
      - Photograph by El Matha Wilder, approximately 1995 (Ovs folder 1, Item 2)
        Study for book jacket cover for God's Country Club.
      - VHS Tape - Author Showcase: Marion K. Barthelme (Ovs folder 1, Item 3)
      - VHS Tape - Houston Women Writers Panel - April 8, 1997, University of Houston Women’s Studies Archives (Ovs folder 1, Item 4)
- Personal Materials, 1970-2016
  This series consists primarily of correspondence, financial records, and photographs.
  - Correspondence with Donald Barthelme, 1970-89 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Cancelled checks, 1980-87 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Program - Cause for Inspiration, An Evening of Celebration benefiting the Jung Center, May 4, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - University of Houston/Creative Writing Program academic transcript for Gail Donohue, 1980-82 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Holiday letters, 1978-2003 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    Holiday letters and poems by Gail Donohue, 1978-81; and by Gail Donohue and C. Porter Storey, M.D., with attached photos, 1992-2003
  - Self-portrait (collage) by Gail Donohue Storey, approximately 1994 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Photographs (Box 8, Folder 39)
    This folder contains photographs of Gail Donohue and Donald Barthelme (circa 1985). Others of Gail Donohue Storey, Porter Storey, Creative Writing Program graduate students, family, friends, childhood home and other residences. Also photos of Gail Donohue Storey by Marion Barthelme for book jacket photo.
  - Boulder Magazine article, Winter/Spring 2007-08 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Biographical articles, 2015-2016 (Box 9, Folder 22)
- University of Houston employment, 1981-2015
  - University of Houston - Publicity, 1981-2015 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - University of Houston - Inprint Board, 1999-2007 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Materials from time as UH Creative Writing Program Admin Director (Box 9, Folder 21)